A Guide to the Papers of Cary Jacob, 1919-1975
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Cary Jacob Papers, 1919-1975
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5629-b
900 items
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Miss Camilla L. Wills, September 13, 1977.
Biographical/Historical Information
Cary Franklin Jacob, 1885-1975, studied at Richmond University and the Peabody Conservatory in Baltimore before attending the University of Virginia where he received his B.S., M.S., and Ph.D. He taught English at the College of William and Mary and speech at Smith College. He left Smith in 1943 and returned to Charlottesville, Virginia, sometime before 1952, where he lived the remainder of his life.
Jacob's writings include articles, speeches, poetry, plays, novels, and short stories as well as preparatory material and the published pamphlet "Freshman English, Manual of Instructions and Exercises." A few articles and a small book of poetry were also published
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains personal papers including biographical data, correspondence, miscellany, and genealogical data regarding John Hough Craven and the Craven, Sneed and Moore families; and manuscripts of Jacob's writings.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series. Series I contains manuscripts and related material. Series II contains personal papers
Contents List
- Manuscripts and Related Material 1914-1956
  - The Fundamentals of Punctuation and Freshman English, Manual of Instruction and Exercises 1925-1939
    - Syllabi and exams for speech courses 1925-1939, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Electrostatic copies of sentences used for grammatical examples. n.d. (Box 1)
    - Grammatical Exercises n.d. (Box 1)
    - Notes regarding Grammatical Exercises n.d. (Box 1)
    - Printed Punctuation Exercises n.d. (Box 1)
    - Written Draft of sections from The Fundamentals of Punctuation n.d. (Box 1)
    - Typed Draft of sections from The Fundamentals of Punctuation n.d. (Box 1)
    - Pamphlet, Freshman English, Manual of Instruction and Exercises 1924 (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Speech regarding America First Committee 1941, 6 TMss (Box 1)
    - Speeches regarding Motion Pictures and Temperance n.d., 2TMss (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - The Psychology of Poetic Talent. 1942, Pamphlet (Box 1)
    - Dean Byron Cummings; The Legend of Guadalupe; and What Every Poet Knows. 1925-1927, 3 TMss (Box 1)
    - Untitled and The American Short Story of Today 1945, 1951, 3 TMss (Box 1)
    - The Fetish of Success - What One Performance of Romeo and Juliet Did Not Lack n.d., 8 TMss (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous poems n.d. (Box 1)
    - Driftwood and Foam 1914 (Box 2)
    - Small collection of poetry ca. 1914, 10 TMss (Box 2)
    - Foreboding In August, To John Marshall, I Wish I Were Ten Men, Insects, and Nocturnal Visitant 1927, 1949, 1951, 1956, 9 TMss (Box 2)
    - To-Day As Yesterday, (also titled Through The Years) ca. 1955 (Box 2)
    - Songs From Street and Field n.d., TMs in hand-bound volume, with miscellaneous copies (Box 2)
    - Autumn Days- Love's Autumn n.d., 22 TMs (Box 2)
    - The Miller of Islington- The While I Think On Thee n.d., 31 TMss (Box 2)
  - Plays
    - Lou 1917, 2 TMss (Box 2)
    - Editor of The Democrat 1918, TMs (Box 2)
    - The Open Shop 1919, 3 TMS (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Facing The Dawn ca. 1928, TMs (Box 2)
    - Heir To The Czar 1930, TMs (Box 2)
    - Ancestors 1932, 2 TMs (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - The Countess Celeste 1945, TMss (Box 3)
      (Different versions of Act Three)
    - The Countess Celeste 1952, TMs (Box 3)
    - The Countess Celeste ca. 1952, TMss (Box 3)
      (Acts One and Two)
    - The Countess Celeste 1952, TMss (Box 3)
    - White Collar 1952, TMs (Box 3)
    - One Family (White Collar) ca. 1952, TMss (Box 3)
    - The Tiger's Claws ca. 1956, TMss (Box 3)
    - At The Bend Of The Road, Miss Beauty O'Connor Sees Her Mistake, The Promotion Of Jim, The Swell Guy, and Why Billy Goes To Bed At Eight n.d., 5 TMss (Box 3)
    - A Man's Work n.d., AMs (Box 3)
    - An Empire For Freedom n.d., TMss (Box 4)
      (Character sketches)
    - An Empire For Freedom n.d., 3 TMss (Box 4)
      (Different versions of Acts One, Two, and Three, 3 folders)
    - In The Path of The Storm n.d., 2 TMss (Box 4)
      (2 folders)
    - In The Path of The Storm n.d., TMs (Box 4)
      (Pages missing)
    - Matrimonial Staircase n.d., TMs (Box 4)
    - Matrimonial Staircase n.d., TMs (Box 4)
    - Red Morning n.d., TMs (Box 4)
    - Red Morning n.d., TMs (Box 4)
      (Section from Act Three)
    - Musical scores, some from play Born Climbin' ca. 1944, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Miscellany n.d., TMss (Box 4)
  - Novels
    - Bitsy Betsy ca. 1953, 3 TMss (Box 5)
      (3 folders)
    - Bitsy Betsy ca. 1953, 2 TMss (Box 5)
      (pages missing, 2 folders)
    - Ancestors n.d., TMss (Box 5)
    - The Bridge n.d., TMss (Box 5)
      (Part One)
    - The Bridge n.d., 2 TMss (Box 6)
      (Parts Two and Three, 2 folders)
    - Facing the Dawn n.d., 3 TMss (Box 6)
      (pp. 1-414, 3 folders)
    - The Mistress of Redbrook n.d., 2 TMss (Box 6)
      (Parts One and Two, pp. 1-219, 2 folders)
    - The Mistress of Redbrook n.d., 4 TMss (Box 7)
      (Part Two, pp. 220-263, Part Three, pp. 364-560, 4 folders)
    - The Order of Brotherly Love n.d., 3 TMss (Box 7)
      (pp. 1-348)
    - Red Hills, also titled Powder a Raven n.d., 2 TMss (Box 8)
      (Books One, Two, Three, and Four, 2 folders)
    - untitled n.d., 2 TMss (Box 8)
      (pp. 1-348, 2 folders)
    - untitled n.d., 2 TMss (Box 8)
  - Short Stories
    - DAB 1923, 2 TMss (Box 8)
    - The Rueing of Randolph Archer ca. 1923, 3 TMss (Box 8)
    - Three Flights Toward the Moon ca. 1925, 3 TMs (Box 8)
    - I Would Have My Own Way 1926, TMs (Box 8)
    - His Lady of Light ca. 1927, 2 TMs (Box 8)
    - Alabama Law to A Blessed Misfortune n.d., 12 TMss (Box 9)
    - A Certain Emanuel to Faces From the Dark n.d., 6 TMss (Box 9)
    - Getting Somewhere to His Good Name and How It Happened n.d., 4 TMss (Box 9)
    - Incorrigible- In the Line of Duty and In the Wake of O. Henry n.d., 4 TMss (Box 9)
    - I Wanted To Be a Lion Tamer n.d., 3 TMss (Box 9)
    - The Janitor's Wife and The Swell Guy to Lord Groton of Groton n.d., 10 TMss (Box 9)
    - Mademoiselle Julie to Peaceable Linkum n.d., 13 TMss (Box 9)
    - Peter, Peter Pumpkin eater to Quick or Dead n.d., 6 TMss (Box 9)
    - Say It With Roses to The Sting of the Rod n.d., 12 TMss (Box 10)
    - A Thwarted Engagement, The Trials of Gemma, and Trustee n.d., 9 TMss (Box 10)
    - We Go to a Bull-Fight to Yaller n.d., 6 TMss (Box 10)
    - Untitled n.d., 5 TMss (Box 10)
    - Odd Moments, Collection of stories n.d., TMss (Box 10)
    - Collection of stories n.d., TMss (Box 10)
- Personal Papers 1917-1974
  - Biographical Data 1942, 1943, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1917-1974, n.d. (Box 11)
    (4 folders)
  - Names and addresses n.d. (Box 11)
  - Genealogical Data for John Hough Craven and relatives n.d. (Box 11)
  - Genealogical Data for Sneed and Moore Family n.d. (Box 11)
  - Legal Documents 1924, ca. 1958 (Box 11)
    (Memorandum of Agreement, and Legal Memorandum regarding Darby vs. Daniel)
  - Famous German Lyrics translated by Alfred Vance Churchill n.d. (Box 11)
  - Typed quotations from various authors n.d. (Box 11)
- Printed Material 1924-1975
  - Magazine Articles 1924, 1928, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Pamphlet, The Rhythm of English Verse by Morris W. Croll 1924 (Box 11)
  - Material regarding D.A.R. Conservation Committee 1972-1974, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Material regarding The Authors League of America 1923, 1962, 1971, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Printed Medical Data and Reading Lists for Tufts Medical School ca. 1935-1939 (Box 11)
  - Propaganda ca. 1934, 1955, 1963, 1968 (Box 11)
  - Clippings 1924, 1962-1974, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous 1937-1944, 1953, 1959-1964, 1971, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Miscellany - General 1929, 1935, 1943-1950, 1966-1975, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Personal Photographs n.d. (Box 11)